Homage to the Buddha Shakyamuni.
Nam mô Phật Bổn Sư Thích Ca Mâu Ni. Kính
Dear all, today
thưa toàn thể đại chúng, hôm nay chúng
we are here, at the place where the Buddha attained
ta được ở nơi đây, nơi Đức Phật thành
enlightenment, known as the stupa of the Buddha's enlightenment and also
đạo gọi là tháp Đức Phật Thành Đạo và
called the Bodhi Gaya
gọi là Bồ Đề đạo
.  Dear fellow devotees, yesterday
tràng. Kính thưa quý đạo hữu, hôm qua
we circled the pagoda three times, and
thì chúng ta đã đi nhiễu tháp ba vòng,
today we have the opportunity to take gold from the
hôm nay chúng ta lại được dắt vàng ở nơi
pagoda's shrine.  Similarly, the stupa enshrines the teachings
tháp thờ. Tương tự Đức Phật tháp thờ lời
of our Buddha upon his enlightenment.  The Venerable
Đức Phật của chúng ta thành đạo. Thì tâm
Master Quan has already shared his thoughts in his videos
chú ông Quán đã chia sẻ trong các video
about the benefits of offering gold as a donation
về việc chúng ta giáp vàng cúng
.  Here, we would like to
dường nhiều rồi. Ở đây chúng con xin
reiterate to the congregation why
nhắc lại cho đại chúng thôi thì tại sao
the Buddha taught us to use newspaper articles
mà Đức Phật dạy chúng ta là dùng bài báo
as offerings at the stupas dedicated to the Buddhas.   The
để cúng dường nơi tháp thờ các đức Phật.
main reason is that when our mind—
Nguyên nhân chính là khi tâm chúng ta
that is, our heart—perceives something as
tức là tâm của chúng ta thấy cái gì còn
precious, then that thing will continue to exist
quý báu thì cái đó còn tồn
.  There.  For example, if a husband and wife
tạ. Đó. Ví dụ như là hai vợ chồng mà
cherish each other, then their feelings for each other will
thấy quý báu nhau thì tình cảm còn tồn
endure, and their family will survive,
tại, gia đình còn tồn tại có phải
right?  And if we see that jade is precious, then
không? Và chúng ta thấy ngọc là báu thì
we will keep it.  If we preserve it,
chúng ta còn giữ. Còn giữ gìn thì nó còn
what will remain?  exist.  But what if something that
tồn gì? tồn tại. Thế còn nếu cái gì mà
our mind perceives is not precious, something
tâm chúng ta cảm tới nó không quý báu,
we don't pay attention to or cherish?
chúng ta không để ý, không giữ gìn thì
What will happen then?  It will rot.  That is the
nó sẽ gì? nó sẽ hoại. Đấy chính là lý
reason why you have met.  As long as our hearts are
nhân duyên các quý đã hữu. Khi tâm chúng
still focused on it, as long as we value it, it will continue to
ta còn hướng tới, còn quý báo thì nó còn
exist.  For example, if
tồn tại. Ví dụ như là khi mà Đức Phật
our Buddha had three times suggested that if
của chúng ta ấy ba lần gợi ý nếu ngài A
Ananda had requested the Buddha to remain in this world,
Nan ấ mà ngài bạch thỉnh Đức Phật trụ
perhaps we would be able to
thế thì có khi bây giờ là chúng ta được
meet the Buddha today.  Therefore,
diện kiến Phật đấy. Thế cho nên tâm
whatever we cherish in our hearts will
chúng ta quý báu cái gì thì cái đó sẽ
endure.  Then we'll all just be made of
còn tồn tại. Thì tất cả chúng ta chỉ
gold.  Although the gold is small and
giác vàng. Tuy rằng vàng nó nhỏ thôi, nó
not of great value, it's used to prevent the
không phải là có giá trị mà để cho cái
brick from rotting.  But it holds
gạch của nó không hoại. Nhưng nó có giá
spiritual value for our esteemed fellow believers.  It
trị trong tâm linh các quý đạo hữu. Nó
holds spiritual significance that there will be a
có giá trị trong tâm linh rằng sẽ có
reason for many people to continue preserving the
nhân có duyên để còn nhiều người giữ gìn
tower.  When something gets old, people
tháp. nó cứ cũ thì mọi người lại tôn
renovate it.  That's it, the intention behind offering to
tạo. Đấy, chính cái tâm cúng dường đến
the Buddha, offering to the Buddha's stupa,
Đức Phật, cúng dường đến tháp thờ Phật
is what the
đó là
Buddha taught.  So, as
ý dạy của Đức Phật là như vậy. Đấy, tức
long as we are still precious,
là khi chúng ta còn quý báu thì nhân
opportunities will continue to arise.
duyên còn phát sinh. Các quý đạo hữu
Do you see, fellow practitioners?  If we were to go
thấy không? Nếu như chúng ta đi dắt
gold hunting or visit Buddhist pagodas, would many people
vàng, tháp thờ Phật thì có nhiều người
want to go gold hunting?  If anyone saw
muốn đi dắt vàng không? Nếu ai xem được
that image, would they?  So,
hình ảnh đó có phải không? Thì cái tâm
what exactly does that desire, that heart that wants to gild everything with gold, entail?
muốn dát vàng ấ thì là cái tâm muốn gì?
We want to maintain, we want to
muốn duy trì, muốn tồn
survive.  Therefore,
tại. Vì thế cho nên là người giát vàng
those who gild Buddha statues or
vào tượng Phật, người giát vàng vào nơi
Buddhist stupas receive such great merit.   The
Phật mới được công đức lớn nao như vậy.
merits of the esteemed members of the district are immense because of their sincere
huyện công đức rất là lớn là bởi vì
hearts. They understand
chính là cái tâm ấy các quý đội hiểu rõ
and desire for this pagoda to
chứ mong muốn cho tháp thờ tháp này tồn
endure forever, and it creates the karmic connection that
tại mãi mãi và nó phát sinh nhân duyên
will lead to people building, maintaining, and
sẽ có những người xây dựng duy trì bảo
preserving it for a long time. That is, it has the karmic affinity to last a
dưỡng lâu dài tức là nó có nhân duyên để
long time. The pagoda is a
tháp trụ lâu dài mà tháp thì chính là
place for us to turn to, a place for us to
nơi cho chúng ta hướng về cho chúng ta
achieve our faith.
thành tựu được tín tâm đế các quý đạo
Isn't it different for the esteemed fellow devotees who come here compared to
hữu sang đến đây có khác mới chúng ta
watching videos at home?
xem video ở nhà không?
At home, we read Buddhist scriptures and
Ở nhà chúng ta có đọc kinh Phật, chúng
we believe in them, but when we come here, our
ta có tin nhưng sang đến đây chúng ta
belief, in the stream of our
cái tin của chúng ta trong cái dòng cảm
feelings, is completely different because
thọ chúng ta thấy khác hoàn toàn bởi vì
this is the truth.  But what else do we
đây là sự thật. Còn kia chúng ta vẫn
hear or see?  Seen through the eyes.
nghe qua tai, nhìn qua gì? nhìn qua mắt.
And it is this karmic connection that leads
Và chính cái nhân duyên mà làm cho chúng
us to believe that gradually brings us
ta tin ấy thì nó khiến chúng ta dần dần
to the state of unwavering faith
vào tới bất thối truyền, lòng tin bất
in the Buddha, an unshakeable belief in Him.  And that is the karmic cause
động với Đức Phật. Và đó chính là nhân
for us to strive and achieve
duyên cho chúng ta tinh tấn và thành tựu
merits, good deeds, and
được các công đức, các việc thiện và
diligently listen to and study Buddhist teachings.  Because we
chăm chỉ nghe học Phật pháp. Do chúng ta
have faith in Buddhism.  Therefore, when we leave,
có tín đối với Phật. Cho nên chúng ta đi
our mindset and faith are
thì cái tâm tín của chúng ta nó khác
completely different, they change entirely.  It changed the
hẳn, nó thay đổi hẳn. Nó thay đổi các
understanding of religious leaders; it instilled in them a firm belief
quý đạo hiểu, nó có một lòng tin vững
in the Buddha.  Because with
chắc vào Đức Phật. Vì nhờ có lòng tin
unwavering faith in the Buddha, we will
vững chắc vào Đức Phật thì chúng ta sẽ
diligently study the Dharma and will no
chăm chỉ học pháp, chúng ta sẽ không
longer have doubts.  So, fellow practitioners,
nghi nữa. Đấy, các quý đạo hữu sang đây
have you noticed any change in your faith after coming here?
có thấy lòng tin mình khác đi không?
They're completely different, aren't they?  Our state of mind is
Khác hẳn đúng không? Trạng thái tâm của
different.   A
chúng ta khác.
different state of mind is a
Trạng thái tâm khác thì là một chúng
different being from the esteemed ones because
sinh khác các quý đại hữu bởi vì chúng
we are merely composed of the five aggregates, esteemed fellow practitioners:
ta chỉ là do ngũ uẩn thôi các quý đạo
form, feeling, perception, volition, and consciousness.
hữu sắc, thọ tưởng, hành thức. Cái hành
Administration is about having that mindset.  So, consciousness
chính là cái tâm ấy. Thế là cái thức
is what we perceive and what
chính là cái chúng ta nhận thấy và chúng
we know.  That's what you all understand.
ta nhận biết. Đấy các quý đạo hiểu đó.
Therefore, when we
Thế cho nên là khi chúng ta được đến
visit sacred sites, make offerings, and
viếng thăm thánh tích, được cúng dường,
receive gold leaf, it carries significant meaning and
được giáp vàng nó có ngần ý nghĩa, có
merit.  There are many
ngần với công đức. Có rất là nhiều công
merits.  And today, I, the mind of the practitioner, would like to share with you, esteemed fellow
đức. Và hôm nay tâm chớ quán chia sẻ với
practitioners, the merit of circumambulating the stupa.
các quý đạo hữu về công đức nhiễu tháp.
The merit of circumambulating the pagoda is something only
Thì công đức nhiễu tháp ấy thì chỉ có
those who participate can receive.
những người nào đi thì mới có được. Còn
Others
người khác
might contribute to us.  Those of us who wear
thì có thể là góp cho chúng ta. Chúng ta
gold armor all receive merit from the noble
giáp vàng thì đều được công đức các quý
practitioners, but the merit of circumambulating this stupa is something only
đạo yu nhưng công đức nhiễu tháp này thì
those who truly want to do it can do.  The
cho có ai đi mới nhiễu được thôi. Còn
rest is simply merit-making at your discretion,
lại thì chỉ là công đức tùy hỉ thôi các
dear fellow practitioners.  As for the largest towers, there
quý đạo hữu ạ. Thì các tháp mà lớn nhất
are only four that are the biggest.  At the time of
thì là chỉ có bốn nơi là lớn nhất. Lúc
the Buddha's birth, enlightenment,
Đức Phật sinh, lúc Đức Phật thành đạo,
turning the wheel of Dharma, and
lúc Đức Phật chuyển pháp luân, lúc Đức
passing into Nirvana, these four stupas were the
Phật nhập Niết bàn là bốn tháp này là
largest, most important, and
lớn nhất, là quan trọng nhất, là công
most meritorious of all the stupas.  Once you
đức nhất trong tất cả các tháp. Quý đợi
understand these four points, your mind will be drawn to the
hiểu bốn chỗ này đó thì tâm ch quấn xin
scriptures and merits of circumambulating the stupa.
đọc văn kinh công đức nhiễu tháp.
Excerpt from the Bodhisattva's Original Conduct Sutra.
trích ở kinh Bồ Tát bản hạnh.
While he was still alive, one day the Buddha and Ananda
Khi còn tại thế, một hôm Phật cùng A Nan
went to the city of Shravasti to beg for alms.  At that time, a
vào thành Xá Vệ khất thực. Bấy giờ trong
Brahmin, coming from outside the city,
thành có Bà La Môn từ ngoài đi vào trông
saw the Buddha, with a radiant halo
thấy Phật với vầng hào quang dạng ngời
around his body, leaving the city.  The
quanh thân đang đi ra khỏi thành. Bà La
Brahmin woman, overjoyed and excited, circled around once in a
Môn vui mừng phấn khích nhiễu quanh một
respectful bow before walking away.
vòng đỉnh lễ rồi bước đi. Thầ kính thưa
Reverend brothers and sisters, in that Brahmanical religion, people show
quý đạo hữu đạo Bà La Môn ấy người ta
great respect to those who practice it.  Dear fellow practitioners,
rất cung kính người tu. Các quý đạo hữu
have you seen those people who are
sang có thấy những cái người mà người ta
gardening or those who are leading
làm vườn hoặc là những người mà di dẫn
tours?  When they see the mind-controlling object, they
tua đấy. Khi họ thấy tâm chế quán thì họ
often bend down, touch their finger to the
hay cúi xuống họ lấy tay họ chấm vào
object of the mind-controlling object, and after touching it once, they
chân tâm chúa quán rồi chấm một xong họ
raise it to their head.  That was an act
đưa lên đầu họ. Cái đấy là một hành động
of my wanting to prostrate myself on the ground, I wanted to prostrate myself at the
của tôi muốn lễ sát đất, tôi muốn lễ
feet.  Are the waiting points clear yet?  Therefore, the
chân. Các cứ đợi hiện rõ chưa? Cho nên
Indians, the
là người Ấn Độ ấy, người dân đạo Bà La
Brahmins, show their respect by
Môn ấy thì người ta cung kính là người
often circumambulating their esteemed friends three times or
ta thường đi nhiễu quanh ba vòng hay
once.
nhiễu quanh một vòng các quý đại hữa.
That is an expression of reverence, meaning that
Cái đó là thể hiện sự cung kính tức là
one's mind is circling around.  The surrounding crowd
tâm mình là đi nhiễu quanh. Nhiễu quanh
is an offering.  You gentlemen understand.
là cúng dường. Các quý đợi hiểu đấy. Tâm
My mental state is just giving one example.  Is there anything so
chế con chỉ đưa ra một ví dụ thôi. Cái
precious that we want to keep
gì mà quý chúng ta có muốn vòng quanh để
looking at it over and over again?  Yes.  Have.
chúng ta xem đi xem lại không? Có ạ. Có.
There.  That is precisely what demonstrates
Đấy. Đấy thì chính cái đấy là thể hiện
the precious heart of our esteemed friends.  That's
cái tâm quý báu các quý đợi hữu. Đấy cho
why Brahmins are very
nên là người đạo Bà La Môn người ta rất
refined and appreciative; they go
là tinh tế, quý báu thì mới đi vòng
around and bow down to their esteemed friends.
quanh rồi lễ xuống các quý đại hữa. Đấy
Therefore, when the Brahmins saw
cho nên là khi Bà La Môn thấy Đức Phật
our Buddha leaving the city carrying his alms bowl to
của chúng ta đi ra khỏi thành ôm bát đi
beg for food, they found
khất thực thì Bà La Môn thấy Đức Phật
our Buddha incredibly majestic.
của chúng ta oai nghi quá.
His radiant light
Hảo quang của
shines forth.  The Buddha was different from
ngài phát ra chiếu sáng. Đức Phật khác
us, my esteemed fellow practitioners. Now, regarding the practice of mindfulness and
chúng ta các quý đạo hữu bây giờ tâm chế
contemplation, I will only briefly mention it.  For example,
quán chỉ nói qua thôi. Ví dụ như sư phụ
is our master different from us?
chúng ta có khác chúng ta không?
Our master, whoever he is, would be
Sư phụ chúng ta là ai đi qua mà nhìn
delighted to see this, wouldn't he?
thấy cũng hoan hỉ phải không? Như chúng
None of us are happy about that.  So,
ta thì chả ai hoan hỉ cả. Cho nên cái
what difference does their appearance make?  They are different.
tướng mạo có khác gì? có khác nhau. Do
Because of their different merits and virtues, their appearances
công đức khác nhau cho nên tướng mạo
differ.  Therefore, our Buddha has
khác nhau. Cho nên Đức Phật của chúng ta
32 auspicious marks, 80 beautiful features, and he possesses
32 tướng tốt, 80 vẻ đẹp và ngài có trí
wisdom; he has all the virtues.
tuệ, ngài có đầy đủ công đức như vậy.
Therefore, it's perfectly normal for an aura to emanate
Cho nên hào quang phát ra là chuyện bình
.  Dear friends,
thường thôi. Các quý đợi hữu ạ. Chúng ta
Sometimes when we read scriptures, we say, "How could a
thì đôi khi đọc kinh lại bảo chứ làm gì
person possibly have an aura emanating from them?"  While some people
người lại có hào quang phát ra. Người
have an unpleasant odor, others
thì đã có mùi hôi phát ra thì có người
need to have a pleasant scent.  Is that right?   Are
phải có mùi thơm phát ra. Có phải không?
there any fellow practitioners present?
Có quý đạo hữu?
The sun still emits sunlight, you know.
Mặt trời còn có ánh sáng mặt trời mà.
Therefore, it is impossible for the Buddha to be
Thế cho nên Đức Phật thì không thể nào
without an aura, my esteemed fellow practitioners
mà không có hào quang được các quý đạo
.  Not everyone can
hữu á. Đó thì không phải ai cũng nhìn
see that halo.  Perhaps at some point the Buddha
thấy hào quang. Có thể lúc nào Đức Phật
wished for everyone to see
muốn cho mọi người nhìn thấy hào quang
this aura; as for what remains, that is a matter of karmic connection, dear
này nhìn còn lại thì nó là nhân duyên
friends.  Then, Venerable Master,
các quý đợi hữu ạ. Đó thế tôn chú quán
please continue reading the scripture.  The Buddha smiled and
xin đọc tiếp văn kinh. Đức Phật mỉm cười
said to Ananda.  When this Brahmin met the Buddha, he was so
bảo a Nan. Bà la môn này gặp Phật liền
joyful that he circled the Buddha once with a
vui mừng nhiễu Phật một vòng với tâm
pure heart.  Thanks to that merit, from now until
thanh tịnh. Nhờ công đức ấy từ nay đến
20 years from now, he will not be reborn
20 năm kiếp về sau, ông ta không bị đọa
into evil paths but will enjoy boundless happiness
vào đường ác mà được hưởng hạnh phúc vô
in the heavenly and human realms.  It is due to a respectful and reverent
cùng ở cõi trời và cõi người. Là do cái
heart
tâm cái tâm cung
towards a worthy person.
kính lễ bái một bậc đáng cung kính. Cho
Therefore, it gives rise to karmic connections and
nên nó phát sinh ra nhân duyên, phát
blessings in this way.  So,
sinh ra phước báo là như vậy. Đấy các
esteemed elders, here, let's examine the situation and use a
quý đại hứa ở đây tâm chế quán lấy một
negative example.  For example, if one of my children has a crush on
ví dụ phản diện. Ví dụ một đứa con của
thugs, will
mình thôi, tâm nó thích cái bọn du côn
they join a gang in the future
thế tương lai nó có đi nhập bọn du côn
?  Is that so?  So, is there a connection, a karmic relationship
không? Có không? Thế là có nhân, có
?  Bao has some fruit.  He
duyên không? Bảo có quả nhá. Tâm nó
likes thugs.  He was always delighted to
thích bọn du côn. Nó luôn luôn vui mừng
hang out with the thugs.  Then
hoan hỉ với bọn du côn. Thế thì duyên
its destiny will lead it to join the ranks of vagrants, and
của nó sẽ gia nhập cái bọn du cơn và cái
its destiny will be to commit evil deeds,
duyên của nó là sẽ làm những việc bất
and the consequence will be suffering, perhaps even
thiện và quả của nó thì đau khổ có khi
imprisonment.  Is that right?  Does
là vào tù. Có phải không? Thế có phải
one cause give rise to many causes
một nhân mà phát sinh ra rất nhiều duyên
?  Similarly, for those who revere
không? Cũng vậy, đối với người cung kính
the Buddha and pay homage to him, they will
Đức Phật, đành lễ Đức Phật thì sẽ phát
create favorable circumstances, my dear fellow
sinh được ngần lấy nhân duyên đấy các
practitioners.  Because the Buddha is a supreme and
quý đạo hữu. Bởi vì Đức Phật là bậc cao
virtuous being, when we show reverence to the Buddha,
tốt mà khi chúng ta cung kính Đức Phật
many beings will protect and support us.
thì có rất nhiều chúng hộ trì chúng ta.
Isn't that right, fellow practitioners?  In a Buddhist
Có phải không các quý đạo hữu? Trong
retreat, for example, if a
chuyến quán lấy ví dụ có một người tu
Buddhist practitioner is joyful in the Dharma,
Phật hoan hỉ với Phật pháp, các quý đạo
would the fellow practitioners immediately
hữu có ngay lập tức ở trong đạo tràng
go to help them from within the monastery?  Yes, there is
bảo nhau đi đến để giúp không? Có không
.  All it takes is for a believer to
có chứ. Chỉ cần có một tín chủ người ta
say, "I want to practice Buddhism."
bảo là tôi muốn tu theo Phật pháp. Lập
Immediately, the head of the Dharma center, the deputy head of the
tức đạo tràng trưởng đạo tràng phó ban
committee, and all of us Buddhists
cán sự rồi tất cả các Phật tử là chúng
volunteered to come and help
ta xung phong đến để chúng ta trợ duyên
.  If we're poor, what can we contribute to?  Give
cho. Nếu nghèo thì góp nhau cho gì? Cho
money.  If someone gets sick, what can we contribute to?  Give the
tiền. Nếu bệnh thì góp nhau cho gì? Cho
medicine.  It's simply because they have a fondness for
thuốc. Cũng chỉ vì một nhân duyên là họ
Buddhism.  Is that right?  Then
mến Phật thôi. Có phải không? Thế rồi
we help them practice Buddhism with
chúng ta lại trợ giúp cho họ tu Phật
what we know is correct, right?  And
những gì mà ta biết có đúng không? Và
that connection lasts for many
cái nhân duyên đó nó kéo dài rất nhiều
days until that person becomes self-reliant and
ngày cho đến khi người đấy tự lực được
no longer needs us.  If you can be self-reliant and
không cần chúng ta nữa. Tự lực được đi
help others, then that's fine.  Is
giúp được người khác thì thôi. Có đúng
that correct?  This helps us understand
không nào? Đó để chúng ta hiểu được một
how many karmic connections can arise in
phát sinh ra bao nhiêu nhân duyên trong
this lifetime for someone who knows about Buddhism.  How did you find out
hiện kiếp như vậy. Đấy là mới biết đến
about this?  It's only through us,
thông qua ai? Thông có chúng ta thôi,
through our masters and monks, that
thông qua sư phụ chư tăng thôi chứ huống
we receive protection. How could a single person who bows to the Buddha, respectfully venerates the Buddha, and circumambraces the Buddha like that not receive the protection of all the benevolent gods and spirits?  Is
thiên thiện thần người ta hộ trì? Có
that right?  Is there a noble path?  How
phải không? Có quý đạo ư? Mà một kiếp
long is the lifespan of a celestial being?  One
sống của chư thiên có dài không? Một
day in the heavens is equivalent to 100 years in
ngày của chư thiên và 100 năm của chúng
our time.  Is that right?  Of course, it's
ta cơ mà. Có phải không? Thì đương nhiên
perfectly normal for such a person to be protected by benevolent deities and gods for countless lifetimes, allowing them to cultivate their spiritual path
kiếp rồi tu tập tác đạo là chuyện rất
.  Can any of you believe
bình thường. Có quý đạo hữu có tin được
this, fellow practitioners?  Yes.  Because
điều này không? Có chứ. Bởi vì sự việc
this is a true story.  He
này là sự việc thật mà. Tầm chên quán
continued reading the scriptures in the inn
đọc tiếp
.  After 25 lifetimes, this man will become a
kinh. Hết 25 kiếp ông này sẽ thành Bích
Pratyekabuddha with the name Tri Than Na Ky Le.  Because of
Chi Phật hiệu là Trì Thấn Na Kỳ Lê. Vì
this karmic connection, whoever circumambraces the Buddha
nhân duyên ấy, nếu người nào nhiễu Phật
or a Buddhist stupa will
hoặc nhiễu tháp Phật thì sinh nơi nào
receive immeasurable blessings wherever they are reborn.  Happiness is
cũng được phước đức vô lượng. Hạnh phúc
not given in abundance?
không cho tràng?
So we circumambulate the Buddha with the intention that the
Thì chúng ta nhiễu Phật với cái tâm là ở
Buddha is here in this way.  The Buddha
nơi đây Đức Phật là như vậy. Đức Phật đã
did these things.  The Buddha possessed so
làm những việc này. Đức Phật có bao
much merit, the Buddha possessed so
nhiêu công đức như vậy, Đức Phật có bao
much wisdom.  When we venerate the
nhiêu trí tuệ như vậy. Chúng ta nhiễu
Buddha with a mind aware of the Buddha and with a
Phật với tâm giác biết về Đức Phật, với
mind full of reverence for the Buddha,
tâm cung kính Đức Phật thì lập tức chúng
we will immediately generate such karmic connections
ta sẽ phát sinh ra các nhân duyên như
in this life and in future lives.
vậy trong kiếp này và các kiếp vị nai.
That is in the public interest.  Today we
đấy là lợi ích của đại chúng. Hôm nay đi
circumambulated the stupa, yesterday we circumambulated the stupa, and
nhiễu tháp, hôm qua đi nhiễu tháp và
during this pilgrimage we visited four
trong chuyến hành hương nhiễu được tứ
sacred sites.  My esteemed friends, we will
thánh tích. Các quý đợi hữu ạ, chúng ta
not only circumambulate the four holy sites, but we will circumambulate
không những nhiễu tứ thánh tích mà tất
all places that bear relics or traces of the
cả những gì có thánh tích, có dấu của
Buddha that we visit on this pilgrimage
Đức Phật trong chuyến hành hương này
.  Your moral character is weak, sir.
hết. C quý đạo yếu ạ.
Then how could we not
Thế thì làm sao mà chúng ta lại không
attain such outstanding merits,
được những công đức thù thắng phải không
my fellow practitioners?  When we are disturbed,
quý đạo hữu? Khi chúng ta nhiễu thì
we visualize the Buddha's presence
chúng ta quán tưởng Đức Phật hiện diện ở
here.  If we persevere with the aspiration for
đây. Chúng ta nhiễu với tâm cầu vô
supreme enlightenment, it will be extremely beneficial.
thượng bồ đề thì thù thắng lắm. Cái ông
This Brahmin was causing trouble with a mind solely
Bà La Môn này ấ ông ấy nhiễu với tâm chỉ
focused on showing reverence to the Buddha.  And
cung kính Đức Phật thôi. Còn chúng ta
what about us?  Understanding the merits of merit.  Is that right
thì gì? Giác biết về công đức. Có phải
?  Do you understand the compassion of the Buddha, that in his previous lives, he
không? giác biết về lòng từ bi Đức Phật
sacrificed himself in this world for three asamkhya eons?   His
kiếp ngài đã xả thân thế này phải không?
compassion for all sentient beings has led him
Lòng từ bi của ngài thương chúng sinh
to practice the Bodhisattva path for the benefit of all beings.
đến này trong việc tu tập vì lợi ích
He has sacrificed
chúng sinh hành Bồ Tát đạo, ngài đã xả
so much of his own flesh and blood, and thus he has achieved
bao nhiêu máu thịt như vậy và ngài thành
so much merit.
tựu với bao nhiêu công đức như thế này.
He has done so much good for all living beings
Ngài làm lợi ích chúng sinh bao nhiêu
.  That is, we are circling the
như thế này. Tức là chúng ta nhiễu các
towers with such a conscious awareness.  And
tháp với tâm giác biết như vậy. Và chúng
we vow to follow in his footsteps.
ta nguyện đi theo bước chân của ngài.
Thus, we have the qualities of reverence
Thế là chúng ta có từ sự từ sự cung kính
, gratitude, appreciation, learning, and making
tri ân, biết ân, học theo và phát
vows.  So, is this considered a great merit, my fellow
nguyện. Như vậy thì công đức có cao tốt
practitioners?  Very good.  And
không các quý đạo hữu? Rất cao tốt. Và
of course, this is an indispensable condition
đương nhiên đây là một nhân duyên không
for us to achieve
thể thiếu cho việc chúng ta thành tựu vô
supreme enlightenment.  And this is a circumstance
thượng bồ đề. Và đây là một nhân duyên
that makes it easier for us to practice.   My esteemed fellow
khiến cho chúng ta dễ dàng tu tập hơn.
practitioners, thanks to the support of
Các quý đạo hữu ạ, vì có sự nâng đỡ của
the realms you are in, it is very
các cõi các quý đạo hữu ạ, rất là lợi
beneficial.
ích.
So, in other groups, it's okay, but I'll
Đó, ở các đoàn khác thì th chứ con sẽ
choose different content, but all of it is
trạch nội dung khác những nội dung nào
very good, so please take the time to watch it.  There.
cũng rất hay và chịu khó mà xem nhé. Đó.
So today we are happy, we are able to
Thế hôm nay chúng ta hạnh phúc, chúng ta
gild the sacred relics with gold to direct our
được rát vàng vào thánh tích để hướng
hearts towards praying that the relics may remain
tâm đến nguyện cầu cho thánh tích được
in the world for a long time, serving as a
trụ lâu dài ở thế gian, làm chỗ quy
refuge for sentient beings, and achieving pure
hướng cho chúng sinh, thành tựu được
faith for all beings, for everyone,
tịnh tín cho chúng sinh, cho mọi người
in the Buddha, Dharma, Sangha, the Triple Gem.  That's my
đối với Phật, Pháp, Tăng, Tam Bảo. Đó
wish.  Now, let us offer our
với nguyện như vậy. Thế
prayers for all the Buddhist practitioners
về nguyện cầu cho tất cả các Phật tử
in our National Buddhist Practice Club
trong câu lạc bộ Quốc bàng tập tu lục
who have wholeheartedly
của chúng ta những người đã hướng tâm
contributed.  Because there are also family members
tới đóng góp. Tại vì còn có người nhà
, relatives, friends, and
nữa, người thân bạn bè nữa, người nhà
all those who are wholeheartedly
tất cả những người hướng tâm tới đóng
contributing, dear friends.  Then they will focus their attention on
góp các quý đợi hữu ạ. Rồi hướng tâm tùy
watching because they have already focused their attention on it
hỉ vì họ đã hướng tâm đến là họ sẽ xem
.  Therefore, that is why I say to you,
mà. Cho nên là tại sao tâm chứ qua nói
esteemed fellow practitioners, you must be dignified,
các quý đạo hữu phải trang nghiêm vì
for your own sake, and for the sake of everyone else as
mình vì mình mà mình lại vì cả mọi người
well.  Even those who are not yet qualified, when
nữa. Những người chưa có đủ điều kiện đi
they see others happy, their hearts are filled with
nữa họ nhìn thấy họ hoan hỉ thế là tâm
joy.  So, are their minds and
hoan hỉ hưỡng về. Thế là tâm họ với tâm
mine in harmony?  Dickens.  Thus,
mình có hòa nhau không? Hòa nhau. Thế là
blessings arise, and karmic connections are formed.
phước báo sinh ra, nhân duyên sinh ra.
Does that mean everyone wins?
Thế có thù thắng cho mọi người không?
Very victorious.  Therefore,
Rất thù thắng. Cho nên là các video nào
we watch all the videos that come our way, regardless of which production team it is
mà xem của đoàn nào chúng ta cũng xem
.  What is it for?  We rejoice in this aspiration,
hết. Để là gì? tùy hỉ để hướng theo, để
hoping that the sacred site will remain for a
mong nguyện cho thánh tích được trụ lâu
long time as a place of refuge for all beings.
dài làm chỗ quy hướng cho chúng sinh.
Each time this happens, it
Thì mỗi lần như thế lại là một lần chúng
creates a karmic blessing that makes it
ta sinh ra phước báo nhân duyên để chúng
easier for us to walk the path to achieving
ta dễ dàng đi trên con đường thành tựu
supreme enlightenment.  That's it, going around the pagoda,
vô thượng bồ đề. Đấy, đi nhiễu tháp mà
those Brahmin couple, after countless lifetimes of being
ông bà la môn kia bao nhiêu kiếp sinh ở
born in the heavenly realms and the human realm, enjoying
cõi trời, sinh ở cõi người, được hưởng
happiness, and eventually attaining
hạnh phúc sau lại được thành đích chi
Buddhahood.  See, aren't we happy now?
phật. Đấy, chúng ta thấy hạnh phúc chưa?
Extremely happy.  And the Buddha said, "Circumambulating
Cực kỳ hạnh phúc. Và Đức Phật bảo nhiễu
the stupa, circumambulating the Buddha—
tháp, nhiễu Phật thì cũng như nhiễu
what's the point of circumambulating him?"  Circumventing the pagoda, circling the Buddha, and
nhiễu gì? Nhiễu tháp, nhiễu Phật và
circling the pagoda.  That's the merit you gain.
nhiễu tháp. Công đức được như vậy đấy.
If we visualize the Buddha as being right
Thì chúng ta cứ quán tưởng Đức Phật hiện
here, and we circumambulate him with
đang ở đây, chúng ta được đi nhiễu với
the intention of following in
cái tâm chúng ta mong muốn theo bước
his footsteps, then surely benefit and
chân của ngài chắc chắn lợi ích, hạnh
happiness will come to us.  So,
phúc sẽ đến chúng ta. Đó, hạnh phúc
are you happy?  Do you, dear fellow practitioners, feel happy
không? Có quý đạo hiữu thấy hạnh phúc
?
không?
Therefore, if you don't dwell on it, just think that you
Cho nên tâm chớ hầ quán thì bảo là mình
also have a fortunate opportunity,
cũng có một cái hữu duyên, cũng có một
that you have the opportunity to lead the group every year
cái hữu duyên đó là hàng năm được dẫn
.  And speaking of interference, he's the one who
đoàn đi. Thế và nói là được nhiễu thao
gets the most interference in the
thì được nhiễu nhiều nhất trong câu lạc
club.  But all that merit is
bộ. Thế nhưng mà bao nhiêu công đức đấy
dedicated to the Buddhists in
cũng hồi hướng hết cho các Phật tử trong
the club, the
câu lạc bộ các quý đạo
esteemed ones. Therefore, I never
yếu cho nên à chưa bao giờ tâm chúa con
thought that I was doing this for myself, not
nghĩ mình đi làm cho mình không phải
entirely for the Buddhists in the
hoàn toàn cho các Phật tử trong câu lạc
club. Even a single piece of gold is dedicated
bộ giáp một miếng vàng cũng hồi hướng
to everyone, so no one is left
hết cho tất cả mọi người không ai thiếu
out, no one is left out. Those esteemed ones, I
xót không ai thiếu xót quý đại yêu đó
pray that everyone will be happy. It's just a matter of whether
thì nguyện mong tất cả chỉ có điều chúng
we direct our hearts towards it or not.
ta có hướng tâm tới hay không hướng tâm
That is our greatest happiness. That's it,
tới thôi đó đây là hạnh phúc tuyệt vời
esteemed ones.
của chúng ta Đấy nhá quý loại hữa. Thế
Therefore, when circumambulating the pagoda,
cho nên khi đi nhiễu tháp thì chúng ta
remember to keep your mind focused.  Tonight we will go back to the
nhớ tránh tâm nha. Tối nay chúng ta lại
pagoda and meditate again.
vào lại nhiễu tháp lại ngồi thiền. Các
Our esteemed fellow devotees here are gilding this,
quý đạo hữu chúng ta này dát vàng này,
offering these flowers, and circumambulating this stupa, isn't that
cúng dường hoa này, nhiễu tháp này có
right?  This method of choosing a spouse is full of
phải không? Rồi gì trạch pháp này đầy đủ
merit, my esteemed friends.  Whatever we can
công đức đấy các quý đợi hữu. Cái gì mà
accomplish on this journey is done with focused concentration,
làm được trong chuyến đi là tâm chú quán
working
làm
together with the demons who sent us, so that
hết cùng với các quỷ đã gửi chúng ta để
we may receive the greatest benefit.  So
chúng ta được lợi ích lớn nhất. Thì Đức
what did the Buddha teach us?  Do you remember those two
Phật dạy chúng ta là gì? Là trong hai
stories where two people came to see the
cái câu chuyện mà hai người đến gặp Đức
Buddha thirsty
Phật mà khát nước ấy, các quý đu nhớ
?  One person wants to pay homage to the
không? Một người thì muốn đến đảnh lễ
Buddha, while another practices the Buddha's teachings.
Phật, còn một người thực hành pháp Phật.
So what did the Buddha say?
Thế cho nên Đức Phật nói gì? Thực hành
What kind of encounters does our practice involve?  Meet me
pháp của ta là diện kiến gì? Diện kiến
.  So, when we share the Dharma
ta. Cho nên chúng ta chia sẻ pháp vào
here, what kind of manifestation of the Dharma Body is that?
đây thì coi như diễn kiến pháp thân gì?
Tathagata.  Consider it an audience with the Buddha.
Như Lai. Coi như diễn kiến Như Lai. Cho
Therefore, everything we
nên tất cả những gì chúng ta chúng ta
do is based on the Buddha's teachings, because only through the
làm là đều lương vào lời Phật dạy để chỉ
Buddha's teachings can we understand
có Phật dạy chúng ta mới biết được thế
what constitutes merit and what creates
nào là có công đức, thế nào là phát sinh
auspicious conditions for us to
nhân duyên thù thắng để cho chúng ta
become Buddhas in the future. Without relying on the
thành Phật sau này thôi chứ không nương
Buddha's teachings, how would we know
và lời Phật dạy chúng ta làm gì biết
?  There.  So, as we
phải không? Đó. Thế thì hôm nay chúng ta
are here today, the Buddha taught the same things,
ở đây thì Đức Phật cũng đã dạy như vậy
and we practice them accordingly.  And
và chúng ta cũng thực hành như vậy. Và
the Buddha greatly desired that his teachings would
Đức Phật rất là mong giáo pháp của ngài
spread widely.  Because if a Buddha preaches the
phổ độ rộng. Bởi vì nếu thành Phật tuyên
Dharma but no one listens to it
thuyết pháp mà lại không ai nghe pháp
anymore, wouldn't all his efforts be in vain?  If no one can
nữa thì có uổng công không? Không ai đàm
discuss the Dharma, will all the effort be wasted?
luận pháp được thì có uổng công không?
So, of all his desires,
Cho nên trong tất cả cái mong mỏi thì
what does the Buddha most desire from us?
Đức Phật mong mỏi nhất chúng ta là gì?
Listening to Dharma teachings, discussing Dharma teachings, and practicing
là nghe pháp, đàm luận pháp và thực hành
Dharma teachings are called listening, contemplating, and cultivating.  Dear fellow practitioners
pháp gọi là văn tư tu. Các quý đạo hữu
, if we don't listen to the Dharma,
ạ, nếu chúng ta không nghe pháp thì
we won't understand the
chúng ta cũng không hiểu thế nào về
precepts, nor the concentration needed to cultivate them,
định để mà tu giới, tu định, tuệ phải
right?
không quý đạo hữu nhé?
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
[Applause]
[Vỗ tay]
Yellow chrysanthemums, rich man, chives.
Hoa cúc vàng quân từ giàu có hẹ. Heéo
Even Heéo's flowers don't fall, they're still pure and noble.
cũng không rơi hoa cũng vàng thanh cao.
Even wealth withers away without
Giàu có héo cũng không phải
color.  The club is also gold, the club of a
màu. Câu lạc bộ cũng vàng, câu lạc bộ
hundred cultivators.
trăm tu. Giàu có
Even if you're rich, you won't be
khó cũng không nan
discouraged; even if you face
lòng, dầu có
difficulties, you'll overcome them
khó cũng sẽ vượt
.  The Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of
qua. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an
Joy.  Practice the Buddhist path to harmony.  The
vui. Tu pháp Phật lùng hòa. Câu lạc bộ
Golden Club, the Club of Joy.  The Dharma of the Buddha,
cung vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Pháp Phật
Lung
Lung
Hoa.  A single flowering stem.  Two flower-shaped guns
Hoa. Một thân hoa đông trụ. Hai khẩu hoa
without a fight.  Third, the idea of ​​the eastern flower is approved.  Four realms of flower cultivation
vô tranh. Ba, ý hoa đông duyệt. Bốn giới
.  The year of the winter flower bloomed.
hoa đồng tu. Năm kiến hoa đông giải.
Six, benefit from the eastern light of the flower.
Sáu, lợi hoa đông quang.
Where there is harmony, there is peace and happiness.  Wherever
Ở đâu có lục hòa, ở đó có an vui. Ở đâu
one practices the six harmonies, there is liberation.
tu lục hòa, ở đó có giải thoát.
[Music] The
[âm nhạc]
Chrysanthemum Club, the Joyful Club.
Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui.
Practice the six harmonies of Buddhism.  The
Tu pháp Phật lục hòa. Câu lạc bộ cúc
Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Joy.  Let's do our
vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Cùng nhau làm
duty together.  The Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of
phận sự. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ
Joy.  Let's practice self-cultivation together
an vui. Cùng nhau tu tí
.  Develop the Bodhi mind.   To
tớ. Phát tâm bồ đề.
uphold the Three Jewels, to spread the Buddha's teachings
Hộ trì Tam Bảo, truyền tải Phật pháp
throughout the world
rộng khắp thế
[music]
[âm nhạc]
.  The yellow chrysanthemum symbolizes
gian. Hoa cúc vàng quân từ màu hoa của
liberation.  The Chrysanthemum Club practices
giải thoát. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng tu tập
meditation to seek liberation and help others.   The
cầu giải thoát giúp đỡ cho mọi người.
Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Joy.
Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui.
Cultivating the mind and seeking liberation, the club is also
Tu tâm cầu giải thoát câu lạc bộ cũng
golden, the club is peaceful and joyful.  The club is also
vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Câu lạc bộ cũng
golden, the club is joyful.
vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui.
[Music] The
[âm nhạc]
Golden Chrysanthemum Club consists of people who have been practicing
Lạc bộ cúc vàng là những người phần từ
Buddhism at
tu tại chùa
Ba Pagoda and always come together to pray for the
Ba luôn cùng nhau tin tán để cầu vô
supreme
thượng
enlightenment.  Let's always believe together that there is no harm in seeking the Emperor's favor
đạo. Luôn cùng nhau tin
.
tể cầu vô thương đã.
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
[Applause] The
[Vỗ tay]
golden chrysanthemum, the soldier from the oil of the pig, does
Hoa cúc vàng quân từ dầu cò heo cũng
not fall, the golden chrysanthemum, noble and
không rơi hoa cúc vàng Vàng thanh cao
wealthy, does not wither, it is not
giàu có héo cũng không phải
the color of the club, it is also golden, the club of a hundred cultivators
màu câu lạc bộ cũng vàng câu lạc bộ trăm
.  Even if wealth is
tu. Giàu có
difficult, it's not impossible; even if
khó cũng không nan
wealth is
lòng giàu có
difficult, it will be
khó cũng sẽ vượt
overcome.  The Golden Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of
qua. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng câu lạc bộ an
Joy.  Buddhist practitioners seek harmony with the
vui. Tu pháp Phật lùng hòa câu lạc bộ
Golden Palace Club.  The club for joyful practice of Buddhist teachings in
cung vàng. Câu lạc bộ an vui tu pháp
harmony.  A single flowering stem.  Two flower-shaped guns
hòa. Một thân hoa đông trụ. Hai khẩu hoa
without a fight.  Third, the idea of ​​the eastern flower is approved.  Four realms of
vô tranh. Ba, ý hoa đông duyệt. Bốn giới
cultivation in the East.  The year of the eastern flower brings six
hoa đông tu. Năm kiến hoa đông giải sáu
benefits and the eastern flower brings light.
lợi hoa đông quang.
Where there is harmony, there is peace and happiness.  Wherever
Ở đâu có lục hòa, ở đó có an vui. Ở đâu
one practices the six harmonies, there is liberation.
tu lục hòa, ở đó có giải thoát.
[Music] The
[âm nhạc]
Chrysanthemum Club, the Joyful Club.
Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui.
Buddhist practice, harmonious living,
Tu pháp Phật lụng hòa, câu lạc bộ cúc
golden chrysanthemum club, joyful club.  Together we fulfill our duties as members of the
vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Cùng nhau làm
Golden Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Peace and
phận sự câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ
Joy.  Let's practice together and I'll
an vui. Cùng nhau tu tí
develop the Bodhi mind.   To
tớ phát tâm bồ đề.
uphold the Three Jewels and spread the Dharma
Hộ trì Tam Bảo, truyền tải Phật pháp
throughout the world.
rộng khắp thế gian.
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
Yellow chrysanthemums, the color of
Hoa cúc vàng quân từ màu hoa của giải
liberation.  The Chrysanthemum Club practices meditation to seek
thoát. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng tu tập cầu
liberation and help others.  The
giải thoát giúp đỡ cho mọi người. Câu
Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Joy.  Cultivate a virtuous
lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Tu
mind to seek liberation.  The club is also
tâm cầu giải thoát. Câu lạc bộ cũng
golden, the club is joyful.  The club is also
vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Câu lạc bộ cũng
golden, the club is
vàng, câu lạc bộ an
joyful.  The Golden Chrysanthemum Club consists of people who have been practicing
vui. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng là những người
Buddhism at Ba Pagoda
phần từ tu tại chùa Ba
and always gather together to meditate and seek the supreme path to
và luôn cùng nhau tính tán để cầu vô
enlightenment.  Let's always be kind and considerate to each other
đạo. Luôn cùng nhau tí
.
tể cầu vô thương đã.
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
[Applause]
[Vỗ tay]
aa golden chrysanthemum, the army from the oil, the pig, even the
aa cúc vàng quân từ dầu cò heo cũng
tears of the golden chrysanthemum, pure and noble,
không rơi lụy hoa cúc vàng Vàng thanh
even if the oil withers, it is not
cao dầu có héo cũng không phải
the color of the club, also golden, the club of a hundred cultivators
màu câu lạc bộ cũng vàng câu lạc bộ trăm
.  Even if wealth is
tu. Giàu có
difficult
khó cũng không nan
, it's not something to be discouraged by; even if wealth is
lòng, giàu có
difficult, it can be
khó cũng sẽ vượt
overcome.  The Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of
qua. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an
Joy.  Practice the Buddhist path to harmony.  The
vui. Tu pháp Phật lùng hòa. Câu lạc bộ
Golden Club, the Club of Joy.  The Buddha's Dharma:
cung vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Pháp Phật
One body, one flower, one pillar; two mouths, one flower, one
hoàng một thân hoa đông trụ hai khẩu hoa
without contention; three minds, one flower, one joy; four realms, one
vô tranh ba ý hoa đông duyệt bốn giới
flower, one cultivation; five insights, one flower, one understanding.
hoa đồng tu năm kiến hoa đông giải. Sáu
Wherever there is harmony, there is peace and joy.
quan ở đâu có lục hòa ở đó có an vui. Ở
Where there is harmony, there is liberation
đâu thu lục hòa ở đó có giải
[in music]
[âm nhạc]
.  The Golden Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of
thoát. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng câu lạc bộ an
Joy.  Buddhist practice involves working in harmony.  The
vui. Tu pháp phật lụng hòa. Câu lạc bộ
Golden Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Joy.  Let's
cúc vàng câu lạc bộ an vui. Cùng nhau
do our duty together.  The Chrysanthemum Club, the
làm phận sự. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu
Club of Joy.  Let's practice self-cultivation together
lạc bộ an vui. Cùng nhau tu tí
.  Cultivate the Bodhi mind, protect the Three Jewels, and
tớ. Phát tâm bồ đề, hộ trì tam bảo,
spread the teachings of Buddhism throughout the world.
truyền tài Phật pháp rộng khắp thế gian.
[Music]
[âm nhạc]
Yellow chrysanthemums, the color of
Hoa cúc vàng quân từ màu hoa của giải
liberation.  The Chrysanthemum Club practices meditation to seek
thoát. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng tu tập cầu
liberation and help others.  The
giải thoát giúp đỡ cho mọi người. Câu
Chrysanthemum Club, the Club of Joy.  Cultivating the
lạc bộ cúc vàng, câu lạc bộ an vui. Tu
mind and seeking liberation: The Golden Chrysanthemum Club.
tâm cầu giải thoát câu lạc bộ cúc vàng.
The Club of Joy.  The club for offering gold.
Câu lạc bộ an vui. Câu lạc bộ cúng vàng.
The Club of
Câu lạc bộ an
Joy.  The Golden Chrysanthemum Club consists of people who have been practicing
vui. Câu lạc bộ cúc vàng là những người
Buddhism at Ba Pagoda
phần từ tu tại chùa Ba
and always gather together to pray for the ultimate
và luôn cùng nhau tính tán để cầu vô
enlightenment.  Let us
đạo luôn cùng. nhau
love each other to pray for no harm
tình để cầu vô thương
[music]
[âm nhạc]